hey everyone welcome to another
interesting lesson in this Tosca course
um today I'm going to talk about
how you can steer your Tosca Commander
using the command line tool which is
also known as DC cell okay this is
provided by Tosca so that you can
execute your scripts not only from Tosca
Commander but from the back end using uh
any command line tool okay
so for Windows we have got command
prompt as you know and we can right away
execute our Tosca test cases right from
here using this particular tool so let's
see how we can do that
in order to access this TC shell which
is the command line tool it is present
in the Tosca Commander installation
folder so one you are installing Tosca
Commander it will be automatically set
up for you okay you just need to access
it and use it
so to access it uh we need to go to that
particular folder and one of the
shortcuts which you can use is Commander
underscore home okay and it is basically
the same folder which is your
installation directory program files
trash Center Commander okay this is
where this particular command line
utility is present
now in order to access this command line
tool uh you don't only need to call it
but you also need to pass some
parameters and these parameters are
basically the workspace path with uh
your credentials for logging into that
workspace
now if you are working in a single user
workspace you don't require any
credentials but in a multi-user
workspace in a real-time scenario you
will require a username and password as
well okay so you need to provide all of
this
and how you can do that is this so it's
basically uh calling the TC cell and
passing the parameters workspace and the
login okay
so in workspace I am giving the
workspace path obviously you need to go
till the tws file which is the actual
workspace file okay
also there are two ways of working with
the TC shelf which is the command line
tool a one is the interactive way and
one is the script way we'll look at both
of them briefly okay starting with the
interactive way uh in interactive way
you can interact with the command line
tool basically so if the command line
tool requires a any input you can
provide them right away in the screen
but in script uh in the script process
you just write the script and prepared
the script once and then you just run
the script so there is no way to
interact with the command line tool in
between the execution okay
so to start off with the interactive
mode uh we required this command TC
shell and then we pass the workspace
so if I copy paste this path here
and then it is going to check for the
license and then it is trying to login
into this workspace okay
for now it is stopped by another process
which is basically the workspace
opened in my Tosca Commander okay so do
keep in mind that you cannot open the
workspace in two places at the same time
unless
you are using a multi-user workspace and
you have got different repositories but
for this particular repository I cannot
access it from the command line and also
from the Tosca Commander I need to close
one of them okay so let's press yes here
okay since uh this is a single user
workspace so it doesn't require username
and password and Tosca already
recognizes that and that's the reason it
didn't ask for any username and password
okay so when you see this prompt that
means you have successfully logged in
into the TC shell and it is connected to
your workspace now okay so now you can
go ahead and run all the commands but
what commands are included in the TC
shell that can be easily uh noted by
this health command okay so when you
write this help command it will show you
all the different options or all the
commands with all the different
parameters okay
the important words are compact
workspace which will basically com uh
compactive works for performance reasons
you can change the node you can call a
script
right uh you can get uh all options get
option you can set different parameters
you can do a health check
okay you can jump to a particular node
so this is what we will see later on
and you can save uh save options uh as I
said set option set property and then
you can also run a particular task so
task is basically uh something like
execution so if you want to execute your
test cases you can use it using this
task okay
so we are going to look at some of these
commands not all of them at least but
the most important ones are the task and
if you want to perform some background
checks like the health check or if you
want to check in all so those things you
can do using this command line tool
okay
so this is the interactive mode uh and
then if I can exit from this interactive
mode
as I said it asks for different
inputs right so it will really ask you
how you want to exit decision or you
want to login into this your workspace
is locked so all of this are inputs
which is asking from the user so that's
the interactive mode but in script mode
you will not find all of these prompts
okay
so I'm now exiting the interactive mode
and let's clear this screen so that we
can see it and then we are going to use
the script mode okay so in script mode
uh apart from these parameters we can
also pass a parameter which contains the
script uh path to the script file okay
so the script.tcs this is the file which
I have created and it contains some
commands or some operations which I want
to perform using the Tosca Commander
okay and if I open this you will see
there are four commands basically first
is jump to node and it contains the node
path uh where my execution list is
present
so the execution list is PDF compare
okay so this will compare to PDF files
and it is inside the execution and
execution lists okay so basically you
have to just look at the uh path of your
particular object and just pass it here
after that I'm
calling the task command to perform some
tasks like clearing the log of the
execution and then running the execution
list and then saving the results so
these are the four commands which I'm
running together in this script.tcs file
okay
now in order to run this I can copy this
whole command okay so this is the script
mode as you remember and we can just
paste it here and we can just start
running our script right from here
so once the script is completed uh it
will post the results back to Tosca
commander and we can go into Tosca
commander and verify their whether the
execution was successful or failed
now
now why this is important is this is the
only way you can integrate your Tosca
test cases with a CI CD tool like
Jenkins right so in Jenkins if you have
got a script uh which you can execute
from Jenkins directly you can automate
your whole execution process or you can
even schedule your executions okay so as
you see uh it is showing all the steps
which is it has performed and it is
saying run finished so let's go to Tosca
commander and let's verify whether it
actually executed that particular
execution list
so if you remember uh we have given this
path which is uh starts from the project
right which is the top node and then
execution then it goes to execution
lists so the first step is to jump to
this particular node which is PDF
compare right and as you can see the
start time stamp
it has been executed just now okay and
the results is fail obviously because
the compare results failed that was
expected but this execution was
performed from the back end which is
from the command line tool right not
from Tosca Commander like the usual way
we do it
and this is more efficient and much
faster obviously because you are doing
it from the back end and you can even
use this process to integrate your Tosca
test cases or execution to uh CI CD tool
okay
so that's our next topic and it will be
very interesting to see how you can run
your test cases right from Jenkins
so do look out for my next session which
is much related to this
and uh we'll talk more about how you can
integrate your Tosca with Jenkins